Guide to the Robert Ferro Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert Ferro papers
1963-1988
YCAL MSS 322
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.5
(11 boxes)
The Robert Ferro Papers consist of personal correspondence and material related to his published and unpublished writings, with a few files of academic and personal papers. The bulk of the collection concerns Ferro's writings, particularly his four novels, which with their semi-autobiographical themes of homosexuality, family, and illness, tell much about his community in the 1970s and 1980s. His earlier writings often refer to his experiences of living in Italy. Ferro also wrote critical reviews for various gay newspapers, and the collection contains snapshot photographs of Gay Pride marches in New York. While his correspondence files are not extensive, they do hold letters from others writers working in the United States and abroad.
Ferro, Robert
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Robert Ferro Estate on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The Michael Grumley Papers (YCAL MSS 323) holds additional personal and business correspondence addressed to both Grumley and Ferro, as well as horoscope and tarot readings; also filed there are all material related to their coauthored volume Atlantis.
Robert Ferro (1941-1988)
Robert Michael Ferro was born in Hoboken, New Jersey, on October 21, 1941. The son of Michael and Gae Panzera Ferro, he was raised in nearby Cranford, New Jersey, with his siblings Michael Jr., Camille, and Beth. While his father was born in America, Ferro's mother had immigrated in 1914 from Italy, a country that would figure prominently in her son's life and writings.
Ferro attended public school in Cranford and in 1963 received a BA in English from Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey. After graduation, determined to become a writer, he lived for a year in Florence, Italy, where he studied Italian and wrote fiction. Ferro enrolled at the Writers' Workshop at the University of Iowa in the fall of 1965; there he studied with the Chilean novelist Jose Donoso and earned a Master of Fine Arts in Creative Writing in 1967. During his final semester at Iowa, Ferro met Michael Grumley (1941-1988), also a student at the Writers' Workshop, and the two began a two-decade-long personal and professional partnership. Known to their friends as "the Ferro-Grumleys," the couple lived primarily on New York's Upper West Side, but also spent extended periods of time in Rome and London. The Ferro family owned an oceanfront home at Sea Girt, New Jersey, which was a place that held particular significance for Robert Ferro: he named the house with a double entendre, "Gaewyck," and designed extensive improvement campaigns for the property. As recorded in Michael Grumley's engagement calendars and daily journals, the pair regularly stayed at the shore house, where they gardened, cooked, read books, and entertained friends and family, while still carving out time to work on their writing projects.
Robert Ferro published five books during his lifetime, four novels and one work of non-fiction, Atlantis: the Autobiography of a Search (Doubleday, 1970), that he coauthored with Michael Grumley. His novels formed what he referred to as a "cycle" of semi-autobiographical writings about homosexuality, the family, and illness. He considered the first, The Others (Scribners, 1977) to be a prologue to the rest: The Family of Max Desir (Dutton, 1983), The Blue Star (Dutton, 1985), and The Second Son (Crown, 1988). Ferro thought the last, in which the lead characters are lovers who both have AIDS, to be his best work. Well received by critics, it was one of the earliest published novels in which the disease features prominently.
Michael Grumley and Robert Ferro were affiliated with a literary group known as the Violet Quill, whose seven members, as men writing for men, are regarded as one of the strongest collective voices of the gay male experience in the post-Stonewall era. Authors Christopher Cox, Andrew Holleran, Felice Picano, Edmund White, George Whitmore, Ferro, and Grumley met several times in 1979, 1980, and 1981 to read aloud from their works in progress. Also on the agenda were discussions of how they could work together to promote recognition, acceptance, and publication of gay literature beyond the boundaries of their own community. Of the VQ writers, Michael Grumley and Robert Ferro were the first to die from AIDS-related complications, both at age 46 in 1988, Grumley on April 28 and Ferro on July 11; they were followed by Whitmore in 1989 and Cox in 1990.
During the 1980s Ferro gave several interviews occasioned by specific book releases, but because his novels were conceived as a cycle, he generally touched upon them all. To his interviewers he spoke openly about the effect his writings had on his family, in particular his father, who was loving and accepting of his son in private life, but became upset when the family's storyline was exposed to the public in print. The death of Gae Ferro from cancer in 1979 was also a pivotal point in the family dynamic, which was further stressed when her death precipitated discussions about selling the Sea Girt property. In interviews, Ferro also talked about the external forces that affected his work, including the state of literature, specifically gay literature, and the looming AIDS crisis then beginning to decimate his own and the larger cultural communities. By the end of his life, Ferro was aware of his place in all those worlds, and expressed his belief that one great value gay writers brought to fiction was truth; having already struggled their way out of the closet, there was little left to fear and much to celebrate in prose. As he observed in one of his final interviews, published in the San Francisco Sentinel a few months before his death, "I understand now that I'm a part of a very important movement in American literature. We are an army of people writing a way of life and writing a history."
Scope and Contents
The Robert Ferro Papers consist of personal correspondence and material related to his published and unpublished writings, with a small selection of academic and personal papers. The bulk of the collection concerns Ferro's writings, particularly his four novels which, with their semi-autobiographical themes of homosexuality, family, and illness, tell much about his community in the 1970s and 1980s; his earlier writings often refer to his experience of living in Italy. Ferro also wrote critical reviews for various gay newspapers, and the collection contains snapshot photographs of Gay Pride marches in New York. While his correspondence files are not extensive, they do hold letters from others writers working in the United States and abroad.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence and Personal Papers (1964-1988); II. Writings by Ferro (1963-1988); and III. Writings about Ferro (1983-1988).
AIDS (Disease); American fiction -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- United States; Gay men's writings, American; Gay pride parades -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; Male homosexuality -- Fiction; Violet Quill (Group of writers); Italy -- Description and travel; LGBTQ resource; Cleaver, Diane; Cratsley, Bruce, 1944-; De Combray, Richard; Elliott, Desmond, 1929-2003; Ferro, Robert; Grumley, Michael; Holleran, Andrew; Kramer, Larry, 1935-; Menegas, Peter; Moses, Charles; Rist, Darrell Yates; Rivers, Ann; White, Edmund, 1940-; Whitehead, William G. (William Grant), 1943-1987; Iowa Writers' Workshop
- Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1964-1988; Series I; 2; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into three subseries: Correspondence; Personal Papers; and Writings of Others
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds correspondence files and a selection of personal papers. The correspondence is primarily personal and that received by Ferro, with a few random copies and drafts of his outgoing letters. The correspondence with his parents, however, is largely two-way. Notable among his correspondents are the Hydra-based American poet and publisher Ann Rivers, and the authors Andrew Holleran and Peter Menegas, from whom there are several folders worth of letters. Ferro kept Holleran's letters (minus their envelopes) in a special box covered in red paper and tied shut with satin ribbons; it has been retained and is stored in box 4. Files of General Correspondence appear at the end of the subseries. Correspondence related to Ferro's writings is filed in Series II.
  Personal Papers includes material related to memorial services for Grumley and for Bill Whitehead, Ferro's editor and friend. There are just four volumes of Ferro's engagement calendars and no personal diaries, but readers seeking information on his daily activities may consult Michael Grumley's papers (YCAL MSS 323), where Grumley's twenty-years-worth of daily journals and calendars record his and the couple's activities, as well as many of Ferro's appointments and events.
  The third subseries contains three folders holding photocopies of writings by Cynthia Ozick, Harold Acton, and Eudora Welty.
  - Correspondence
    - Andrews, John
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Peter Menegas Menegas, Peter
    - Barbrook, Marguerite, 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boyle, Nichola, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Burns, Camille Ferro, and family, 1968-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Clemons, Walter, 1977-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cratsley, Bruce, 1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      General note
      Includes a brief essay on Cratsley's work by Ferro
    - Donoso, Jose, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ferro, Gae and Michael, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Ferro, Kathleen, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ferro, Michael Jr.
    - Grumley, Michael, 1978-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Holleran, Andrew, 1967-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
    - Indiana University, Bloomington. Creative Writing Program, 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes copies of essays submitted prior to application for graduate program
    - Ingram Merrill Foundation, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Iowa Writers' Workshop, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Kramer, Larry, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lipscomb, Dennis, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Marx, Frank P., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Menegas, Peter, 1970-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
      Folder 25 contains material on applications to the United States Immigration and Naturalization Service handled by Michael Ferro for Menegas's lover John Andrews (Yiannakis Eftychiou)
    - Moses, Charles, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Rivers, Ann, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Stambolian, George, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Streeter, Colin, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Svare, Richard, 1974-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - White, Edmund, 1981-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence with potential literary agents, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Christmas cards, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - General correspondence, 1965-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 34-38)
  - Personal Papers
    - Aptitude test, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Birth certificate (copy), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Blackglama mink advertisement parodies, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Design for a monument, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Dinner party menus, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Engagement calendars, 1981-1981 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
    - Engagement calendars, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Fellowship, residency, and grant applications, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Ferro, Gae P.
      - Condolence cards and letters, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
      - Obituary, 1979 May 27
      - Research paper on antisemitism, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Gay network mailing lists ("Bill Whitehead address file"), undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Includes lists used for party invitations, book distribution, etc.
    - Grumley, Michael, memorial service, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Hofstra University, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Medical papers, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
    - Photographs, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Includes portraits of Ferro, and snapshots of and with friends; several were taken at Gay Pride events in New York
    - Real estate
      - Italy, Rome, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - US, New York, Jones Point/Mead's Hollow, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - US, New Jersey, Sea Girt, 1985-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 59-61)
    - Resumes, circa 1964, circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Tarot and other readings, 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Tax records, 1970-1987 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Travel documents, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Whitehead, William G., memorials, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      Includes tribute essays by Ferro, Stanley Elkin, Doris Grumbach, and Edmund White.
    - Miscellaneous ephemera, notes, drawings, 1963-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
      Includes a portrait by Michael Grumley, possibly of Ferro
  - Writings of others
    - Letters (1982-1985) from Cynthia Ozick to William Whitehead, photocopies from E.P. Dutton office files, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - From Memoirs of an Aesthete, by Harold Acton, photocopy, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - "Learning to See," by Eudora Welty, photocopy, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Box that formerly held Andrew Holleran's letters, undated (Box 4)
- Writings by Ferro, 1963-1988; Series II; 6; (6 boxes)
  The series is organized into three subseries: Books; Reviews; and Other Writings
  The subseries Books contains files of correspondence, drafts, reviews, and fan mail for Ferro's four published novels, The Blue Star (1985), The Family of Max Desir (1983), The Others (1977), and Second Son (1988). The subseries Reviews contains typescripts and tear sheets of Ferro's work for four periodicals, Advocate, Christopher Street, New York Native, and Philadelphia Gay News, with some related correspondence. Other Writings holds academic papers from his graduate school days, novels and short stories that went unfinished or unpublished during his lifetime, ideas for screenplays and musicals, and a few poems he composed. The largest sets of files in the subseries document his more extensive work on two book-length projects, "Chiaroscuro," and "The Minnehaha Bequest"/"The Finishing Touch," the latter co-written with Michael Grumley. The subseries also contains a paper, "Gay Literature Today," that Ferro presented at Oberlin College in November 1987; it later appeared in the anthology The Violet Quill Reader.
  All files on Atlantis: the Autobiography of a Search, which was co-authored with Michael Grumley, are held in Grumley's papers (YCAL MSS 323).
  An excerpt from Ferro's last novel Second Son appeared in the anthology Men on Men: Best New Gay Fiction (1986); material related to that project is with the files for his novel.
  File titles in quotes were taken from the author's annotations or from his original folders/envelopes/containers
  - Books
    Arranged in alphabetical order by book title
    - The Blue Star (1985)
      - Notes and correspondence, 1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - "The Bartolini," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - "Changes in first draft of Bartolini," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Miscellaneous pages from "The Bartolini," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - "The Secret of Temple Park," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - "Love Without Wings," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - Chapters 11-14, holograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 77-78)
      - "Excerpt from a novel, The Blue Star," typescript and photocopy, [1985] (Box 5, Folder 79)
        Possibly sent with National Endowment for the Arts grant application
      - Fan mail, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - The Family of Max Desir (1983)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - Draft pages, typescript and photocopy (in no order), undated (Box 5, Folder 83-85)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 86-87)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 88-89)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, corrected ("Walter's copy"), 1982 (Box 5, Folder 90-91)
      - Excerpt: "Black Madonna," (published in Christopher Street ), undated (Box 5, Folder 92)
      - Excerpt: "The Ripple Effect", undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
      - Excerpt: "The Voice", undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
      - Setting copy, undated (Box 5, Folder 95-96)
      - Master galley, 1983 Mar 15 (Box 5, Folder 97)
      - Galley, author's corrected copy, 1983 Apr (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - Blurbs for dust jacket, [1983] (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - Party invitation and distribution lists, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 100)
      - Publicity and reviews, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Fan mail, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Paperback edition cover, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - The Others (1977)
      Includes drafts composed under the working titles "The Voyage of the Balalaika" and "The Others"
      - Correspondence
        - Boyle, Nichola
          See Series I
        - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1976-1980 (Box 6, Folder 104)
        - Hash-Marc, Inc., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 105)
        - Murray, Angus Wolfe, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 106)
        - General, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 107)
      - Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 108)
      - "The Voyage of the Balalaika"
        - "1st draft original", undated (Box 6, Folder 109)
        - "First draft for Story, written in Rome", 1970 Aug (Box 6, Folder 110)
        - "Original typescript", undated (Box 6, Folder 111-112)
        - "Second draft original," "finished New York", 1971 Nov (Box 6, Folder 113-114)
        - "Second draft carbon", undated (Box 6, Folder 115)
        - "2nd draft," photocopy, undated (Box 6, Folder 116)
        - "3rd draft," "author's copy", 1974 Apr 12 (Box 6, Folder 117-118)
        - "Final draft, rough copy", 1976 Jul (Box 6, Folder 119)
        - "3rd or 4th draft," "final copy for copy editor", undated (Box 6, Folder 120-121)
        - "Final copy, with corrections", undated (Box 6, Folder 122-123)
        - Random draft pages from "The Voyage of the Balalaika", undated (Box 7, Folder 124-125)
      - "The Others"
        - Typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 7, Folder 126)
        - Random draft pages, undated (Box 7, Folder 127-129)
        - Drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 130-132)
        - Draft, carbon, "re-edited September 1983" and "refinished Jan 1986", 1983-1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 133)
      - Inscriptions in copies, [1977] (Box 7, Folder 134)
      - Reviews, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 135)
      - Fan mail, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 136)
      - The Others, published volume, annotated by Ferro: "corrected copy - Jan 1985", 1977, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 137)
      - Screenplay, undated (Box 7, Folder 138)
    - Second Son (1988)
      - Manuscript notes and drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 139)
      - "First draft," chapter 1, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 7, Folder 140)
      - Draft, chapter 1, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 141)
      - Galley for chapter 1, published in Men on Men: Best New Gay Fiction (1986), 1986 Jun 3 (Box 7, Folder 142)
      - Draft, chapter 2, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 143)
      - "First draft," typescript photocopy, incomplete, undated (Box 7, Folder 144-145)
      - "Second draft," typescript photocopy, corrected, 1987 Jun (Box 7, Folder 146-147)
      - Draft, undated (Box 7, Folder 148-149)
      - Flap copy, [1988] (Box 7, Folder 150)
      - Publicity, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 151)
        See also: Series III, Writings about Ferro
      - Reviews, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Reviews
    - Advocate, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 153)
    - Christopher Street, undated (Box 8, Folder 154)
    - New York Native, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 155)
    - Philadelphia Gay News, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 156)
  - Other Writings
    - Academic writings, 1965-1967
      - Assignments and papers, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 157)
      - Thesis notes, [1966-1967] (Box 8, Folder 158)
      - Thesis notebooks, [1966-1967] (Box 8, Folder 159-162)
    - "Apotheosis", undated (Box 8, Folder 163)
    - "Beginnings and Endings", circa 1965 (Box 8, Folder 164)
    - "Chiaroscuro"
      - Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 8, Folder 165)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 166-173)
      - Miscellaneous draft pages, undated (Box 8, Folder 174)
    - "Conch Pearl," screenplay, by Ferro and Michael Grumley, undated (Box 8, Folder 175)
    - "Frank's Party", undated (Box 8, Folder 176)
    - "Gay Literature Today", [1987] (Box 8, Folder 177)
      Lecture delivered at Oberlin College, November 18, 1987; later published in The Violet Quill Reader (1994)
    - "Hello, Sailor", undated (Box 8, Folder 178)
    - "High Altars", 1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 179-181)
      Contains short stories: High Altars; A Hole in the Floor; Of February; Sex with the Belgian; The Daytime Moon; Bullfight, a Carnival, a Bus Ride; Chores; Towards a Better Understanding; Florence in the Rain.
    - "Ideas, Notes on Novel", undated (Box 9, Folder 182)
    - "The Medicine Man," by Ferro and Michael Grumley, 1972-1975, undated (Box 9, Folder 183)
    - "The Minnehaha Bequest"/"The Finishing Touch"
      Coauthored by Ferro and Michael Grumley, under the pseudonyms Christopher Nash and Alec Sassoon
      - Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 184)
      - Synopsis sets, undated (Box 9, Folder 185-187)
      - Notes and draft pages, 1972, undated (Box 9, Folder 188)
      - Drafts, 1975, undated (Box 9, Folder 189-199)
    - "The Naked Lobe", undated (Box 10, Folder 200)
    - "The 96th St. Crosstown," by Ferro and Michael Grumley, undated (Box 10, Folder 201)
    - "Quietly en Famille", [1968] (Box 10, Folder 202)
    - "Report from Florence", 1963 (Box 10, Folder 203)
    - "River of the City's Dream", 1969 (Box 10, Folder 204)
    - "Specimens", undated (Box 10, Folder 205)
    - "White Water", circa 1965 (Box 10, Folder 206)
    - "Work in Progress", undated (Box 10, Folder 207-208)
      Combination of typescript and typescript carbon pages with holograph corrections; pages in no order; title pages bear addresses in Iowa and Puerto Rico
    - Notes for proposed musical/s by Ferro and Michael Grumley, 1986, undated (Box 10, Folder 209)
    - Miscellaneous literary notes, drafts, typescripts, undated (Box 10, Folder 210-215)
    - Miscellaneous literary notes, drafts, typescripts, undated (Box 10, Folder 216-228)
    - Notebook with miscellaneous writings, 1980-1988, undated (Box 10, Folder 229)
      Contains draft section of "Max Desir," some personal letters, and autobiographical writing; also contains drafts of poetry by Michael Grumley
    - Miscellaneous poems, 1974-1981 (Box 10, Folder 230)
- Writings about Ferro, 1983-1988; Series III; 9
  The series is organized into two subseries: Interviews; and Articles.
  The series contains interviews with Ferro, which are a combination of clippings, audiotape transcriptions, and handwritten responses to prepared questions. It also includes articles in which Ferro's work is prominently featured or described.
  - Interviews
    - Burke, Robert Emmett. Interview for New Castro Times, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 231)
    - Gora, Tom. Interview for In Style for Men, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 232)
    - Hoctel, Patrick. Interview in San Francisco Sentinel, 1988 Mar 25
    - Reed, Paul. Interview in Bay Area Reporter, 1988 Mar 10